Guide to the H. Lee Waters Film Collection, 1936-2005 (bulk 1936-1942)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Lexington (N.C.), circa 1937-1945
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 59:40, including footage of Lexington (N.C.), circa 1935-1953) (Box 29)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, duplicate (Box 29)
- Liberty (N.C.), circa 1936-1939
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1936 September 25-26; 1939 December 11-12.
  Screening Theatre: Curtis Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1, (1600 ft.) (Reel 3)
- Lillington (N.C.), circa 1939
  Screening Date: 1939 September 21-22.
  Use Copies: DVD and VHS use copies available, reel 3 of 3. Shot list available, reel 3 of 3, see box 33.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 3 of 3, (300 ft.) (Box 6)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 3, (200 ft.) (Box 15)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 3, (600 ft.) (Box 15)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reels 1 and 2 of 3 (Box 23)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, reel 3 of 3, (TRT: 10:26) (Box 29)
- Louisburg (N.C.), circa 1936-1937
  Screening Date: 1937 January 14-15.
  Screening Theatre: Not listed.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (300 ft.) (Box 6)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 15)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 23)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 10:25) (Box 29)
- Madison (N.C.), 1940 April 01
  Screening Date: 1940 April 29-30.
  Screening Theatre: Patovi Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (400 ft.) (Box 6)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (500 ft.) (Box 6)
- Madison (N.C.) and Mayodan (N.C.), circa 1939-1941
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1939 January 05-06; 1939 March 23-24; 1940 April 29-30; 1941 September 29-30; 1941 December 15-16.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 2, (900 ft.) (Box 6)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 3, (1000 ft.) (Box 7)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 3 of 3, (1400 ft.) (Reel 2)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 3 (Box 15)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 3 (Box 15)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 3 of 3 (Reel 12)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 3 (Box 24)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 3 (Box 24)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 3 of 3 (Reel 14)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, reels 1-2 of 3, (TRT: 71:52) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, reel 3 of 3, (TRT: 56:22) (Box 30)
- Martinsville (Va.), circa 1937-1939
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1937 December 01-02; 1939 February 01-02.
  Screening Theatre: National Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (500 ft.) (Box 7)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (400 ft.) (Box 7)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reels 1-2 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reels 1-2 of 2 (Box 23)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 35:20) (Box 30)
- Mebane (N.C.), 1939
  Screening Date: 1939 December 14-15.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (600 ft.) (Box 7)
- Mooresville (N.C.), circa 1937-1939
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1937 August 12-13; 1938 June 23-24; 1939 August 21-22.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (1100 ft.) (Box 7)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (850 ft.) (Box 7)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 24)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 24)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 77:41) (Box 30)
- Mt. Airy (N.C.), 1941
  Screening Date: 1941 October 08-09.
- North Wilkesboro (N.C.), circa 1937-1941
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1937 January 04-05; 1938 November 07-09; 1939 June 05-06; 1941 March 03-04; 1941 October 13-14.
  Screened at one of the following theatres: Liberty Theatre (1937); New Orpheum Theatre (1938-1939); Allen Theatre(1941).
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (1600 ft.) (Reel 6)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 2 of 2, (1200 ft.) (Reel 5)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Reel 13)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 2 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, reel 1 of 2, (TRT: 44:59) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, reel 2 of 2, (TRT: 28:06) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, color segments, reel 2 of 2, (TRT: 11:01) (Box 30)
- Oxford (N.C.), circa 1938-1941
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1938 August 17-18; 1938 October 05-06; 1939 November 01-02; 1941 April 03-04.
  Screened at one of the following theatres: Carolina Theatre (1938-1939); Orpheum Theatre (1941).
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (1300 ft.) (Reel 7)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Reel 10)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 36:22) (Box 30)
- Pilot Mountain (N.C.), circa 1939
  Screening Date: 1939 May 15-16.
  Screening Theatre: Pilot Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (500 ft.) (Box 7)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (300 ft.) (Box 7)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 24)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 24)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 27:45) (Box 30)
- Raeford (N.C.), circa 1938
  Screening Date: 1938 April 21-22.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (800 ft.) (Box 8)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (circa 400 ft.) (Box 8)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 16)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, reel 1 of 2, (TRT: 22:20) (Box 30)
- Reidsville (N.C.), circa 1936-1942
  Screening Date: Not listed.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (400 ft.) (Box 8)
- Roxboro (N.C.), circa 1936-1937
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1936 November 16-17; 1937 March 01-02.
  Screening Theatre: Dolley Madison Theatre.
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (600 ft.) (Box 17)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 24)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 15:46) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 15:46) (Box 31)
- Roxboro (N.C.), circa 1937
  Screening Date: 1937 March 01-02.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (300 ft.) (Box 8)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 24)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 10:40) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 10:40) (Box 31)
- Roxboro (N.C.), 1938
  Screening Date: 1938 September 08-09.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (400 ft.) (Box 8)
  - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 8)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 20:13) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 20:13) (Box 31)
- Roxboro (N.C.), 1939
  Screening Date: 1939 July 13-14.
  Screening Theatre: Dolley Madison Theatre and Palace Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (800 ft.) (Box 8)
  - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 8)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 35:05) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 35:05) (Box 31)
- Roxboro (N.C.), circa 1940
  Screening Date: 1940 July 11-12.
  Screening Theatre: Palace Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (900 ft.) (Reel 1)
  - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 8)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 40:00) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate (Box 31)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 40:00) (Box 31)
- Roxboro (N.C.), circa 1941
  Screening Date: 1941 May 01-02.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (300 ft.) (Box 8)
  - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 8)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 16:00) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate (Box 31)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 16:00) (Box 31)
- Roxboro (N.C.), circa 1936-1941
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1936 November 16-17; 1937 March 01-02; 1938 September 08-09; 1939 July 13-14; 1940 July 11-12; 1941 May 01-02.
  Screened at one of the following theatres: Dolley Madison Theatre (1936-1938, 1941); Dolley Madison Theatre and Palace Theatre(1939); Palace Theatre (1940).
  Use Copies: VHS use copy available.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (500 ft.) (Box 8)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 21:00) (Box 30)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate (Box 31)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 21:00) (Box 31)
- Rutherfordton (N.C.), 1937
  Screening Date: 1937 June 28-29.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (800 ft.) (Box 9)
- Salisbury (N.C.), 1940
  Screening Date: 1940 November 11-12.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (1200 ft.) (Box 9)
  - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 9)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 18)
  - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 18)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Color separation print, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 63:00) (Box 31)
- Scotland Neck (N.C.), 1939
  Screening Date: 1939 November 20-21.
  Screening Theatre: Dixie Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (700 ft.) (Box 9)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 18)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 18:58) (Box 31)
- Siler City (N.C.), 1937-1942
  Screening Dates: 1937 May 06-07; 1939 November 15-16; 1941 March 20-21; 1942 March 23-24.
  Screening Theatres: Gem Theatre (1937); Elder Theatre (1939-1942).
  Contains footage from multiple Waters films shot between 1937 and 1942.
- Smithfield (N.C.) and Selma (N.C.), 1937
  Screening Date: 1937 June 07-08.
  Screening Theatres: Howell Theatre (Smithfield, June 07) and Selma Theatre (Selma, June 08).
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (400 ft.) (Box 9)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (400 ft.) (Box 9)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reels 1-2 of 2 (Box 18)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 46:30) (Box 31)
- Spindale (N.C.), 1937
  Screening Date: 1937 July 22-23.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (1100 ft.) (Box 9)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 18)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 25)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 33:55) (Box 32)
- Statesville (N.C.), 1940
  Screening Date: 1940 November 25-27.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (300 ft.) (Box 10)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (300 ft.) (Box 10)
  - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 2 of 2 (Box 10)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 18)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 18)
  - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 18)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 26)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 26)
  - Color separation print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 26)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 28:48) (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, duplicate (Box 32)
- Swannanoa (N.C.), 1938
  Screening Date: 1938 October 24-25.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (500 ft.) (Box 10)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 19:30) (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 19:30) (Box 32)
- Taylorsville (N.C.), 1939
  Screening Date: 1939 June 29-30.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (700 ft.) (Box 10)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 25:00) (Box 32)
- Thomasville (N.C.), circa 1938-1939
  Screening Date: 1939 January 25-26.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (500 ft.) (Box 11)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 51:30, including footage of Thomasville (N.C.), circa 1936-1940) (Box 32)
- Thomasville (N.C.), circa 1936-1940
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1936 August 06-07; 1937 November 24-25; 1939 January 25-26; 1940 February 12-13.
  Screened at one of the following theatres: Palace Theatre (1936, 1940); State Theatre (1937-1939).
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (500 ft.) (Box 11)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (400 ft.) (Box 11)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 19)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 19)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 26)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 26)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 51:30, including footage of Thomasville (N.C.), circa 1938-1939) (Box 32)
- Troy (N.C.), circa 1936-1940
  Screened on one of the following dates: 1936 December 07-08; 1938 January 06-07; 1939 January 30-31; 1940 May 08-09.
  Screening Theatre: Troy Theatre (1938-1940).
  Includes footage of Star, Biscoe, Candor, and Mt. Gilead.
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (1300 ft.) (Box 19)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (1200 ft.) (Box 19)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, reel 1 of 2, (TRT: 50:13) (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, reel 2 of 2, (TRT: 45:50) (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, reel 1 of 2, (TRT: 50:13) (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate, reel 1 of 2 (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, reel 2 of 2, (TRT: 45:50) (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, duplicate, reel 2 of 2 (Box 32)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, duplicate, reel 2 of 2, (TRT: 45:50) (Box 32)
- Whitmire (S.C.), circa 1938-1939
  Screening Date: 1939 February 20-21.
  Screening Theatre: Strand Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1, (400 ft.) (Box 11)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19)
  - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 17:00) (Box 33)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 17:00) (Box 33)
- Winnsboro (S.C.), 1936
  Screening Date: 1936 December 04.
- Wytheville (Va.), circa 1939
  Screening Date: 1939 April 28-29.
  Screening Theatre: Wythe Theatre.
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2, (400 ft.) (Box 11)
  - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2, (400 ft.) (Box 11)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 19)
  - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 19)
  - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, (TRT: 34:00) (Box 33)
  - Preservation tape master, Betacam SP, (TRT: 34:00) (Box 33)
- Related Materials, circa 1936-2005
  - Ephemera (Box 33)
    Contains a canister, stills, and VHS copies of Tom Whiteside's 1989 film The Cameraman Has Visited Our Town and the January 1990 NBC Nightly News story on H. Lee Waters. The box also includes a DVD with footage of ColorLab's Julia Nicoll separating the film base from the emulsion of the Chester (S.C.) H. Lee Waters film. Contains some preserved footage from Chester.
  - Advertisements, undated (Opaperfolder 1)
  - H. Lee Waters Movies of Local People Records, 1936-1942 (Box 34)
    Waters' indexed log book.
  - Advertisements, circa 1960s and undated
  - Notes, receipts, and correspondence, 1972-1974 and undated
  - Martin Johnson's master thesis, 2005
  - Shot lists, undated
  - DVD Duplicating Masters (Box 35)
    This box contains the DVD duplicating masters for the Waters films.